Finding aid for University Herbarium (University of Michigan) Records, 1744-1745, 1851-1981, and 2001-2014
Bentley Historical Library
University Herbarium (University of Michigan) records
1744-1755
1851-1981
2001-2014
1890-1955
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. University Herbarium.
2014136 Aa2
36.5 linear feet
The University of Michigan Herbarium, started in 1837, is home to over 1.7 million species and is one of the world's leading botanical collections. The U-M Herbarium records collection includes correspondence, photographs, and research materials documenting early Herbarium history, U-M's ethno botanical research practices, and the international professional discourse surrounding botanical research.
This record group was received from the University Herbarium (donor no. 10914 ) in April, 2013 and from the University of Virginia Mountain Home Biological Station (donor no. 11062 ) in February, 2014.
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The history of the U-M Herbarium goes back to the November 18, 1837 Board of Regents meeting where Henry Schoolcraft presented a resolution calling for a "Committee on the Library, Philosophical Apparatus, and Cabinet of Natural History" which led to the appointment of Dr. Asa Gray as the first University of Michigan Professor of Botany and Zoology (Bartlett, 13). In 1838, the Herbarium's original collections were started due to state geologist Douglass Houghton's first geological survey of Michigan. In 1839, Dr. Houghton was appointed as Professor of Geology and Mineralogy, and the collected specimens were placed under his supervision. During the 1840s, the collections were moved into Mason Hall and the University continued to receive donated specimens, including from Dr. Houghton and from Abram Sager (Mains, 1442-1443).
In 1855, the collections were gathered into the developing natural history museum under the direction of Alexander Winchell. At this time, the botanical specimens were under the same purview as geological and zoological specimens. Through the 1860s and 1870s, the Herbarium continued to receive donations, including from botanists Dr. George L. Ames, Josiah T. Scovell, Mary O. Rust, and Marcus Baker. These collections were placed under the now established Museum of Zoology. To manage the collections, Mark Walrod Harrington was appointed as an assistant and cataloged the collections. In addition, Louisa M. Reed and Elizabeth C. Allmendinger provided voluntary support to develop the herbarium and catalog the collections. Ms. Allmendinger engaged in plant switching with other institutions and published a list of plants within the Ann Arbor area, donating her personal collection to the herbarium (Ibid., 1443-1446). Throughout this time, professors in the Department of Botany were active in development of the collections. This established a norm where botany professors concurrently acted as curators of herbarium collections.
In 1876, Assistant Professor Joseph Beal Steere and Volney M. Spalding were placed in charge of the herbarium's collections. In 1879, Steere was given the official title of Curator for the museum. An 1881 reorganization of the museum by the Board of Regents split the management of the geology, zoology, and botany collections, stipulating that the professor in charge of instruction for a given topic should be the curator of its museum collection. As the Professor of Botany, Volney M. Spalding thus became curator. In the same year, the collection moved into the newly constructed museums building, with a new herbarium workspace established in 1893. During this time, although the Museum of Zoology had the official herbarium collections, the Department of Botany maintained a separate herbarium collection (Ibid., 1446-1447; Bartlett, 9).
The early 20th century saw significant changes for the botanical collections and the ultimate formation of the U-M Herbarium. In 1904, Spalding resigned, and Frederick Charles Newcombe was appointed Professor of Botany while Charles A. Davis was appointed curator of the collection. In addition, in 1905, the state legislature passed a bill establishing a new biological survey of Michigan under state geologist Alexander G. Ruthven. Due to the increasing collections, and increased interest in the collections, in 1908 staff numbers increased and in 1912, the curation of the collection was split into Curator of Cryptogamic Herbarium (Calvin H. Kauffman) and Curator of Phanerogamic Herbarium (Henry A. Gleason). A disastrous fire in 1913 destroyed a significant portion of the collections and a new museums building was not completed until 1915. To grow the collection, many new donations were received, including from Charles Keene Dodge, of the Michigan Biological Survey. Dodge's collection of 35,000 specimens was curated separately under Cecil Billington.
The herbarium as it stands today was established in 1921 under Director Calvin H. Kauffman. In 1921, the botanical collections, the herbaria of the Department of Botany, the herbarium in the Museum of Zoology, and Dodge's collections were united into the Herbarium of the University of Michigan and given a separate budget. Kauffman and John H. Ehlers were appointed curators, with Cecil Billington as an Honorary Curator. In 1926, Dr. Bessie B. Kanouse was appointed Curator and Assistant to the Director. By 1929, the Herbarium contained nearly 185,000 specimens in classified collections, and 75,000 undistributed specimens. This same year, the Herbarium purchased the collections of Professor Bruce Fink, adding over 16,700 specimens to the collection and bringing Joyce Hedrick Jones to the University as a research assistant (Mains, 1447-1449).
In 1930, an agreement between the Carnegie Institution and the University of Michigan led to biological surveys of Central America, including British Honduras, Guatemala, and Mexico, until the cooperation ended in 1939. Several U-M faculty members and staff participated in expeditions, including the Botanical Gardens Director Harley H. Bartlett, Joseph B. Steere, and Cyrus Lundell. These studies grew the Herbarium collections considerably and led to many publications about botanical research in Central America. The Second World War interrupted the activities of the herbarium. Several herbarium staff took leaves of absence to assist with the war effort, including explorations in South America for the Board of Economic Warfare, and Professor Bartlett's work with the armed forces advocating botanical collection by armed forces abroad (Ibid., 1450-1451). Following the war, the botanical collections grew significantly with continued botanical expeditions and due to donations by botanists such as A.H. Poval, Paul M. Rea, E. B. Copeland, and Harley H. Bartlett (Ibid., 1454; Rogers & Shaffer, 3-4). The acquisition of Harley H. Bartlett's specimens changed the Herbarium's collections from a predominantly locally-focused institution into a large, international research collection. (Rogers & Shaffer, 4) After 1975, the collecting policies of the Herbarium shifted towards diversifying the collections through targeted gifts and exchanges rather than through field work, however field work has continued in North America and Mexico. In 1956, the Herbarium was absorbed into the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, remaining as a separate unit until July 1, 2011 when it became part of the Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology (Reznicek).
The Herbarium's later research projects began with Professor Edward Voss' Michigan Flora Project, which started in 1956 and lasted for more than 40 years. The Michigan Flora Project led to the publication of the three volume Michigan Flora series and the Herbarium's current Michigan Flora database. In addition to the Michigan Flora Project, the U-M Herbarium contributed to several projects, including the International Code of Botanical Nomenclature, Flora Novo Galiciana, Flora of North America, Mosses of Mexico, Mosses of the Great Lakes Forests, Flora of China, and Flora of the Venezuelan Guyana. In 1974, the Herbarium was designated by the American Society of Plant Taxonomists as one of the 25 National Resource Center Collections in the United States and was ranked as one of the top three herbaria in the country. The U-M Herbarium is also a leader in digitizing herbaria collections, beginning with a 1977 database of seed plant types (Reznicek). The U-M Herbarium currently houses one of the best botanical collections in the world, housing over 1.7 million specimens, including renowned collections of vascular plants, algae, bryophytes, fungi, and lichens.
Early Curators
1839-1846 Douglas Houghton
1846-1848 Silas H. Douglass
1848-1855 Abram Sager
1855-1873 Alexander Winchell
1868-1876 Mark Walrod Harrington
1868-ca. 1881 Joseph Beal Steere
1873-1875 Eugene Woldemar Hilgard
ca. 1866-ca. 1882 Elizabeth C. Allmendinger
ca. 1873-ca. 1889 Louisa M. Reed (Stowell)
1876-1904 Volney M. Spalding
1905-1908 Charles A. Davis
1905-1908 Brown Forest Buffen H.
1912-1920 Calvin H. Kauffman
1912-1916 Henry A. Gleason
1916-1918 John H. Ehlers
1918-1921 Cecil Billington
Directors
1921-1930 Calvin H. Kauffman
1931-1959 Edwin B. Mains
1959-1972 Alexander H. Smith
1972-1975 Rogers McVaugh
1975-1986 Robert L. Shaffer
1986-1999 William R. Anderson
(1994-Acting Director) Anton A. Renicek
1999-2002 Gerald R. Smith
2003-2005 David P. Mindell
2006-Current Paul E. Berry
Later Curators
1926-ca. 1960 Bessie B. Kanouse
1930-1966, 1976-1982 William Randolph Taylor
1934-1959 Alexander H. Smith
1944-1959 Joyce Hedrick Jones
1945-1950 William Campbell Steere
1946-1979 Rogers McVaugh
1960-1996 Edward G. Voss
1960-1993 Robert L. Shaffer
1960-1991 Warren H. Wagner, Jr.
1965-1995 Howard A. Crum
1978-2003 Robert D. Fogel
1978-Current Anton Reznicek
1997-2006 Michael J. Wynne
-------------------
References:
Bartlett, Harley H. The History of Botany at the University of Michigan through the First Century, 1837-1937. Bentley Historical Collection, Herbarium records, Box 21, folder 1. c.1951.
Mains, Edwin B. "History of the University of Michigan Herbarium, 1837-1953. http://um2017.org/2017_Website/History_of_Herbarium.html. 1956.
McVaugh, Rogers and Robert L. Shaffer. History of the University of Michigan Herbarium, 1940-1970. http://um2017.org/2017_Website/History_of_Herbarium_2.html. 1976.
Reznicek, Anton. Recent History of the University of Michigan Herbarium (1976-present). 2013.
The collection represents the Herbarium's actions as a collector of the historical correspondence and photographs of botanical researchers. The records contained within this collection primarily document the research methods and professional conversations of American botanists. Through the correspondence and papers of Michigan and U-M botanists, this collection also documents the development of the Herbarium, its activities, and its status as a collector of botanical specimens and historical records. Researchers should note that there are photographs and plant specimens scattered throughout the correspondence series, and whereas the plant specimens are noted in the box listing, the photographs are not. The collection's four series include Harley Harris Bartlett Papers, Herbarium Historical Correspondence, Herbarium Historical Photographs, and Archived Website.
Batak (Indonesian people); Botany.; Botany -- Pictorial works.; Ethnology.; Ethnology -- Pictorial works.; Indonesia -- Description and travel.; Mycology.; Philippines -- Description and travel.; Botany.; Black-and-white negatives.; Photographs.; Bartlett, Harley Harris, 1886-1960.; United States. Bureau of Plant Industry.; United States. Office of Rubber Investigations.; University of Michigan. Department of Botany.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan. Matthaei Botanical Gardens.; University of Michigan. University Herbarium.; Allmendinger, Elizabeth C., 1837-1909.; Clemens, Mary Strong, 1873-1968.; Davis, Charles Albert, 1861-; Dodge, Charles Keene, 1844-1918.; Ehlers, John Henry.; Hanes, Clarence R. (Clarence Robert), 1874-1956.; Herbst, William.; Jones, Joyce, 1897-1980.; Kanouse, Bessie Bernice, 1889-; Kauffman, C. H. (Calvin Henry), 1869-1931.; McIlvaine, Charles, 1840-1909.; McVaugh, Rogers, 1909-2009.; Mains, E. B. (Edwin Butterworth), 1890-1968.; Merrill, Elmer D. (Elmer Drew), 1876-1956.; Rea, Paul Marshall, 1878-; Sterling, Edward Boker.; Tuckerman, Edward, 1817-1886.
- Bartlett, Harley Harris, 1744-1855; 1875-1959
  The Harley Harris Bartlett Papers series, 1744-1959 (27.25 linear feet), documents the career and research interests of Professor H. H. Bartlett, who served as the Director of the Botanical Gardens from 1922 to 1955 and as chairman of the University of Michigan Department of Botany from 1922 to 1947. This series contains seven subseries: Index, Bureau of Plant Industry Correspondence, Correspondence and Associated Materials, Family Correspondence, Personal Correspondence, Photographs, and Special Interest. The Correspondence and Associated Materials, Photographs, and Special Interest subseries were collected and curated by the Herbarium and are arranged to conserve the Herbarium's order as established in the index. Researchers should note that the Bentley Historical Library also has a separate collection of Bartlett's papers received from the Bartlett Estate (call no. Aa/2; 85701). Due to the distinct provenance of the two collections, and the Herbarium's curation of this Bartlett series, the two collections are maintained separately.
  - Index, undated (Box 1)
    The Index subseries, undated (0.1 linear feet) consists of the U-M Herbarium's original catalog for the Correspondence and Associated Materials, Photographs, and Special Interest subseries. It includes substantial supplemental information including dates, locations, and correspondents. The Bureau of Plant Industry Correspondence, Family Correspondence, and Personal Correspondence subseries were not curated by the Herbarium and are not included in the index.
  - Bureau of Plant Industry Correspondence, 1910-1915
    Bureau of Plant Industry Correspondence, 1910-1915 (0.4 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, consists of Bartlett's professional correspondence while working for the Bureau as a chemical biologist.
    - A-W, 19 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Associated Materials, 1875-1959
    Correspondence and Associated Materials, 1875-1959 (18 linear feet), arranged alphabetically, consists of Bartlett's personal and research correspondence as well as other materials including research journals, Department of Botany materials, Botanical Gardens materials, plant samples, and photographs. This subseries also documents Bartlett's activities as a collector, containing the correspondence, and research notes of Mary Strong Clemens and Elmer D. Merrill. The correspondence includes Bartlett's activities as a professor, the director of the Botanical Gardens, management of the Herbarium, and his relations with collectors, researchers, and botanical libraries. The subseries also contains Bartlett's bibliography and research journals related to Bartlett's international expeditions in Sumatra, the Philippines, Argentina, and Formosa. The subseries also contains correspondence, personnel questionnaires, and governmental policies related to botanical research by armed forces during World War II, including by Company D, 3651st Service Unit. The subseries includes correspondence with many notable scientists and U-M faculty, including Hugo de Vries, Bruce Fink, Alexander H. Smith, Rogers McVaugh, and Charles C. Deam. {Mary Strong Clemens' research notebooks, indicated in the index, were not transferred from the Herbarium in this accession.}
    - A
      - A.A.A.S., 1937-1945 (Box 1)
        (correspondence and papers)
      - Abbot, C.G., 1928-1944 (Box 1)
        (Smithsonian) Greene's "Landmarks")
      - Abbot, Waldo, 1946 (Box 1)
        (radio programs, Bot. staff dept.)
      - Abbott, Herschel G., 1954 (Box 1)
        (Juniperus communis and Asa Gray Bulletin)
      - Abcede, J.B., 1955 (Box 1)
        (cortisone from yams (Philippines)
      - Abeel, Neilson (Box 1)
        (see Pacific War Memorial)
      - Abegg, F.A., 1926; 1928 (Box 1)
        (re position; appreciation)
      - Acosta, Carmen, 1950 (Box 1)
        (student help (Puerto Rico))
      - Acosta-Solis, Misael, 1936-1952 (Box 1)
        (Ecuador)
      - Adam, Tassilo, 1929; 1941; 1947 (Box 1)
        (re Batak col., lecture, etc.)
      - Adams, James P., 1946-1951 (Box 1)
        (Provost, U of M)
      - Adams, Mary I., 1946 (Box 1)
        (reply to student applicant)
      - Adams, R.L., 1947 (Box 1)
        (staffing, U. Philippines)
      - Aunt Adelia, 1907-1912 (Box 1)
        (personal-family)
      - Africa, Bernabe, 1948-1950 (Box 1)
        (Philippines)
      - Aga-Oglu, Kamer, 1940-1948 (Box 1)
      - Aguilar, Hernan D., 1943 (Box 1)
        ("rubber")
      - Alban, Sister Mary, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
        ("plant collecting")
      - Albany Museum (South Africa), 1929 (Box 1)
        (fossil coals)
      - Uncle Albert & Aunt Mary, 1938 (Box 1)
      - Albertson, John G., 1945 (Box 1)
        ("Armed Forces collecting")
      - Alcorn, Gordon D., 1939 (Box 1)
        (reply to student)
      - Alder, George G., 1936 (Box 1)
        (double blood root)
      - Alexander, Taylor R., 1954 (Box 1)
        ("big trees")
      - Ali, J. Mohammad, 1925 (Box 1)
        (alien deportation case)
      - All Nations Club, U of M, 1945 (Box 1)
        (election to Advisory Comm.)
      - Alland, Alexander, 1941 (Box 1)
        (re photographs of plants in Virgin Isis.)
      - Allee, Ralph H., 1947 (Box 1)
        (inter-American forestry)
      - Allen, Charles E., 1921; 1928; 1939-1940 (Box 1)
        (botanical)
      - Allen, Dorothy Ann, 1927(?)-1929 student application (Box 1)
      - Allen, Edward S., 1911-1945 (Box 1)
        (personal-Harvard)
      - Allen, Glenn W., 1924 (Box 1)
        ("Allen walnut")
      - Allen, Minne E., 1920 (Box 1)
        (personal, Mrs. Edward S. Allen)
      - Allen, Paul H., 1941 (Box 1)
        (botanical C.Z.)
      - Allied Geographic Sect., S.W. Pacific Area, 1945 (Box 1)
      - Allison, Ira S., 1951 (Box 1)
        (carbon dating)
      - Alm, Ragnar, 1934-1936 (Box 1)
        (plant collecting)
      - Almy, Robert F., 1941 (Box 1)
        ("Wilkes Exped.")
      - Alpert, Harry, 1955 (Box 1)
        ("Fire & Prim. Agr.")
      - Alsberg, Carl L. (Box 1)
        (see Nat'l. Res. Council-Fellowships)
      - Altenburg, Clarence E., 1955 (Box 1)
        (reply to invitation)
      - Amangini, 1956 (Box 1)
      - American Agar & Chem. Co., 1942 (Box 1)
        (., agar production)
      - American Association Botanical Gardens & Arboretums, 1940 (Box 1)
        (organization of assn.)
      - American Association Univ. Wm., Flint, 1944 (Box 1)
        (re speaking)
      - American Bible Society, 1920 (Box 1)
        (Philippine dialects)
      - American Committee for non-Participation in Japanese Aggression, 1940 (Box 1)
      - American Council, Inst. of Pacific Relations 194-1 invitation to membership (Box 1)
      - American Ethnological Soc., 1934 (Box 1)
      - American Genetic Association, 1927 (Box 1)
      - American Library Association, 1946 (Box 1)
      - American National Red Cross, 1949 (Box 1)
        (appr. of stamps sent to patients)
      - American Philosophical Society, 1931-1958 (Box 1)
      - American Polar Society, 1958 (Box 1)
        (re stamp honoring Wilkes exped.)
      - American Society of Agronomy, 1957 (Box 1)
        (invitation to charter member)
      - American Society of Naturalists, 1949 (Box 1)
        (suggestions for revitalization of Soc.)
      - Ames, Oakes, 1937-38, 1948 (Box 1)
        (orchid collections)
      - Ammann, George A., 1945 (Box 1)
        (A.F. collecting-Kiska)
      - Amsden, Monroe (Box 1)
      - Anderson, Edgar, 1941-1949 (Box 1)
        (maize, popcorn)
      - Anderson, E.G., 1919-1933 (Box 1)
        (genetics, teaching)
      - Anderson, Jacob P., 1945-1946 (Box 1)
        ("Flora of Alaska")
      - Anderson, Joe N., 1940 (Box 1)
        (student)
      - Anderson, John E., 1933-1938 (Box 1)
        (ex-student, problems)
      - Anderson, Leland R., 1945 (Box 1)
      - Anderson, Mouritz G., 1945 (Box 1)
      - Andrews, A. LeRoy, 1910 (Box 1)
      - Andrews, D. (Box 1)
      - Andrews, Louis C., 1916 (Box 1)
      - A.F. collecting recommendation Sphagnum (Box 1)
      - Angeles, Mrs. Mildred M., 1949 (Box 1)
        (re Philippines)
      - Angell, Virginia, 1929 (Box 1)
        (Crataegus (student))
      - Angstman, O.E., 1932 (Box 1)
        (bulbs)
      - Ann Arbor mayor-Walter C. Sadler, 1940 (Box 1)
        (recreation)
      - Ansell, Emily, 1928 (Box 1)
        (Far East curios)
      - Anthony, Harold E., 1946 (Box 1)
        (collecting in Africa)
      - Anthony, Margery, 1945-1949 (Box 1)
        (student-collected in Texas)
      - Apostles' Club, photo-1922 (Box 1)
      - Arber, Agnes, 1949 (Box 1)
        (botanical books)
      - Archer, William A., 1928-1934; 1941 (Box 1)
        (see also 1) Carpelan Exped.)
      - Arcilla, Lucar, 1950 (Box 1)
      - Arctic Institute of North America, 1947-1952 (Box 1)
        (plant expl. in Arctic)
      - Arkansas State Geological Survey, 1949 (Box 1)
        (radioactive areas)
      - Armstrong, George M. (Clemson), 1934 (Box 1)
        (re position-Ralph Wilson)
      - Army Medical Museum, 1946 (Box 1)
        (requesting material)
      - Army Post Offices, 1945 (Box 1)
        (A.F. collecting)
      - Arnaldo, Solomon V., 1943 (Box 1)
      - Arnold, Chester A., 1928-1947 (Box 1)
        (staff, U of M)
      - Arnold, H.H., 1954 (Box 1)
      - Arsene, Bro. G., 1937 (Box 1)
        (Eragrostis)
      - Arsenio Manuel, E., 1954 (Box 1)
      - Artiaga, Santiago, 1946-1955 (Box 1)
      - Arwidsson, Th., 1939-1946 (Box 1)
        (Sumatran rusts)
      - Asa, K., 1913 (Box 1)
        (acknowledgment)
      - Asa Gray Bulletin, 1951-1958
        - Abrahams, Harold J., 1958 (Box 1)
          (re ms)
        - Bacigalupi, Rimo, 1955 (Box 1)
          (publication)
        - Baehni, Charles, 1953 (Box 1)
          (subscription)
        - Baur, Harold L., 1956 (Box 1)
          (material for publication)
        - Bernatowics, Albert J., 1953 (Box 1)
          (ms)
        - Bierhorst, J. W. (Box 1)
        - Bingham, Marjorie T., 1955 (Box 1)
        - Biographical material: Ernest A. Bessey, Robert B. Canfield, John H. Davis, Jr., Elizabeth Downhour, Constance G. DuBois, Adolph D. E. Elmer, David Fairchild, Oliver Farwell, Edward S. Parsons, Cornelius L. Shear, Paul W. Thompson, Warren G. Waterman, Rene Vandendries (Box 1)
        - Brunel, Jules, 1952 (Box 1)
        - Chase, Virginius, 1953-1955 (Box 1)
          (photographs, ms)
        - Conard, Henry S., 1952 (Box 1)
        - Core, Earl L., 1953 (Box 1)
          (The Southern Appalachian. Botanical)
        - Club in, 1953 (Box 1)
        - Dansereau, Pierre, 1954 (Box 1)
        - Dean, Don, 1952 (Box 1)
        - Drews, Robin A., 1957 (Box 1)
          (return of ms)
        - Dupree, A. Hunter, 1954 (Box 1)
          (Ms)
        - Eyerdam, Walter J. (Box 1)
          (collecting in the Aleutians)
        - Financial records (Box 2)
        - Forays: Okoboji Lake Foray 1952, 1953 Central States Foray, 1954 Everglades, So. Florida, 1954., 1952-1954 (Box 2)
          (Black Hills Foray,)
        - Grant, Martin L., 195? (Box 2)
        - Gray Mem. Chap., Agassis Association, 1891-, also M.K. Swingle (Box 2)
        - Gunn, Charles R., 1955 (Box 2)
        - Hanes, Clarence R., 1953 (Box 2)
        - Jeffreys, M.D.W., 1957 (Box 2)
        - Jenkins, Anna E., 1954 (Box 2)
        - Keane, K.S., 1952 (Box 2)